Guide to the Muslims in Brooklyn oral histories 2018.006
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Oral History Interview with Abdul Hafeez Muhammad, October 21, 2018; 2018.006.51
  In this interview, Abdul Hafeez Muhammad discusses his childhood in the Canarsie neighborhood of Brooklyn, including his adopted family; his early exposure to violence and mortality; and his exploration of the Five Percent Nation. He speaks at length about his subsequent involvement with the Nation of Islam under Louis Farrakhan, especially regarding his marriages, his service as assistant minister and minister within local mosques, his memories of Farrakhan's speech at Madison Square Garden in Manhattan in 1985; and his work with educational and religious outreach to incarcerated Black men. He also talks about his advocacy within the broader Black community, particularly regarding the Million Man March in 1995 in Washington, D.C. Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.
  African American Muslims -- New York (State) -- Kings County; African American religious leaders -- New York (State) -- New York; Black Muslims -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Canarsie (New York, N.Y.); Children -- Death; Harlem (New York, N.Y.); Civil rights demonstrations -- New York (State) -- New York; Cultural pluralism -- New York (State) -- New York; Islam -- Customs and practices; Islamic religious education -- New York (State) -- New York; Marriage -- Religious aspects -- Islam; Muslim converts -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Muslim religious leaders -- New York (State) -- New York; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001; Farrakhan, Louis; Five Percent Nation; Muhammad Mosque No. 7C (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Oral History Interview with Mohammed Fayaz, October 22, 2018; 2018.006.52
  Mohammed Fayaz was born in 1990 in Brooklyn. He was raised in the Jamaica Estates and Middle Village neighborhoods of Queens. As a young adult, he channeled his creativity into art, with a particular focus on depicting people of color. He created early promotional materials for the group Papi Juice, which was founded to celebrate queer and trans people of color, and became one of their core organizers.
  In this interview, Mohammed Fayaz discusses his Muslim Indian family, especially their immigration to the United States; their religious and cultural traditions; and their experiences following the September 11 terrorist attacks in 2001. He speaks about his exploration of his culture, gender identity, sexual orientation, and Muslim faith; his development as an artist; and posting his artwork on social media. He elaborates on the promotional artwork and organizing he has done for Papi Juice; the group's focus on creating "intentional spaces" for queer people of color; and his friendships with founders Oscar Nñ and Adam Rhodes. He also talks about his decision to move to the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. Interview conducted by Zaheer Ali.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Children of immigrants -- New York (State) -- Queens; Coming out (Sexual orientation) -- New York (State) -- Queens County; Cultural pluralism -- New York (State) -- New York; Gay artists -- New York (State) -- New York; Gender nonconformity -- New York (State) -- New York; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Queens County; Intersectionality (Sociology); Islam -- Customs and practices; Islamophobia -- New York (State) -- New York; Jamaica (New York, N.Y.); Muslim artists -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Muslim gays -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Queer culture; Queer identity; Religion and culture; South Asians Americans -- New York (State) -- New York; Queens (New York, N.Y.); Nñ, Oscar; Rhodes, Adam
- Oral History Interview with Misba Abdin, December 17, 2018; 2018.006.53
  Misba Abdin was born in 1969 in Beanibazar, Bangladesh. He immigrated to the United States with his family in 1982 and settled in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn. Shortly after arriving, he organized a series of local soccer tournaments called the Bangladesh Football Federation (later renamed to Bangladesh Sports Council). He married his wife in 1995 and later founded the Bangladeshi American Community Development and Youth Services (BACDYS) in East New York in 2011.
  In this interview, Misa Abdin discusses his family; his life in Beanibazar, Bangladesh; and his immigration to the United States. He expands on his experiences in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn over the years, including his organizing a local series of soccer tournaments called the Bangladesh Football Federation (later renamed the Bangladesh Sports Council); his ongoing involvement with the local mosque his father co-founded, Masjid Al-Aman; and his founding the Bangladeshi American Community Development and Youth Services (BACDYS). He also speaks about his encounters with violent crime and the New York City Police Department; Islamophobia; and racism. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  Bangladeshis -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Child rearing -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Community organization -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Cultural pluralism -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Education of children -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Hate crimes -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islamophobia -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Police-community relations -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Racial profiling in law enforcement -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Religious pluralism -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Social service -- New York (State) -- Kings County; New York (N.Y.). Police Department
- Oral History Interview with Sharmin Hoque, December 21, 2018; 2018.006.54
  Sharmin Hoque was born in 1994 in Noakhali, Bangladesh and immigrated to the United States with her family in 1999. She was raised in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn and the Ozone Park neighborhood of Queens. After earning her bachelor of the sciences in public health from Long Island University and her master of public health in sociomedical sciences from Columbia University, she focused on improving New Yorkers' access to mental health services through her work as a research coordinator at NYU Langone and as the vice president of Muslims Thrive.
  Sharmin Hoque discusses her family; her upbringing in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn and the Ozone Park neighborhood of Queens; and her impressions of Baitul Mamur Masjid and Masjid Al-Aman, both located in East New York. She speaks extensively about studying public health at Long Island University and Columbia University; her work as a research coordinator at NYU Langone and as the vice president of Muslims Thrive to improve access to mental health services for Bangladeshi and Muslim New Yorkers; and her observations about the intersections between race, religion, and mental health. She also talks about her marriage to her husband; her faith; her experiences with racial profiling and Islamophobia; and her thoughts about gender roles within Muslim communities. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  Bangladeshis -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Hijab (Islamic clothing) -- New York (State) -- New York; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islam -- Prayers and devotions; Medicine -- Religious aspects -- Islam; Mental health -- Religious aspects -- Islam; Mental health services -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Patient education -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Police-community relations -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Public health personnel -- New York (State) -- New York; Women in Islam -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); East New York (New York, N.Y.); Ozone Park (New York, N.Y.); Queens (New York, N.Y.); Columbia University; Long Island University; NYU Langone Medical Center
- Oral History Interview with Kobir Chowdhury, January 10, 2019; 2018.006.55
  Kobir Chowdhury was born in 1974 in the Sylhet District in Bangladesh. He immigrated to the United States in 1991 and settled in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn. He worked in real estate and banking after arriving in New York. He also attended Masjid Al-Aman in East New York and began to take on leadership roles in the mosque in the 2010s, including serving as an advisor to the executive committee and as the president of the mosque's board.
  In this interview, Kobir Chowdhury discusses his childhood in Bangladesh; leaving his family behind when he immigrated to the United States alone as a teenager; and settling in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn. He expands on his work in the service industry, real estate, and banking after arriving in New York; his continued ties to his home village in the Sylhet District in Bangladesh; and his involvement with Masjid Al-Aman in East New York. He also talks about his Muslim faith, his marriage to his wife, and raising their son. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); East New York (New York, N.Y.); Ozone Park (New York, N.Y.); Queens (New York, N.Y.); Sylhet District (Bangladesh); Bangladeshis -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Child rearing -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Crime -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Faith-based human services -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islamic religious education of children -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Religion and ethics; Religion in the workplace -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Real estate investment -- New York (State) -- Kings County
- Oral History Interview with Firoza Akter, January 22, 2019; 2018.006.56
  Mst. Firoza Akter was born in 1981 in Bangladesh. She moved to Dhaka as a teenager to pursue higher education and married in 2002. She immigrated to the United States to join her husband shortly after the birth of their first child in 2005. They settled in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn, where she became involved in both Baitul Mamur Masjid and Muslim Ummah of North America (MUNA). With MUNA, she worked to engage youth in their community's cultural and religious traditions; plan community events; and provide social and material assistance to people in need.
  In this interview, Mst. Firoza Akter discusses her family, her childhood in Bangladesh, and moving to Dhaka to pursue higher education as a teenager. She expands on her marriage to her husband, her immigration to the United States, and raising their children in the East New York neighborhood of Brooklyn. She speaks at length about her involvement in East New York's Bangladeshi community and her work with the faith-based community organization Muslim Ummah of North America (MUNA). She also talks about Bengali cultural traditions; her Muslim faith; gender roles within East New York's Muslim communities; and her experiences with Sharmin Hoque (interviewed for this collection on December 21, 2018) and her family. Interview conducted by Liz H. Strong.
  Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Dhaka (Bangladesh); East New York (New York, N.Y.); Bangladeshis -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Child rearing -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Community centers -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Cultural pluralism -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Education of children -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Faith-based human services -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Immigrants -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Islam -- Customs and practices; Islam -- Prayers and devotions; Muslim women -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Religion and ethics; Ummah (Islam) -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Women in Islam